Guide to the John M. Chowning Papers SC0906
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
John M. Chowning papers
1974-2014
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Chowning, John M.
SC0906
1.5 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Collection consists largely of correspondence between Chowning, the Yamaha Corporation, and the Technology Licensing Office at Stanford, 1974-97; other items include patents and related documents, 1978-87, technical writings (not all by Chowning), 1974-87, publications and leaflets on Yamaha products, and miscellaneous notes. The technical writings include “Excerpts from Computer Music Proposal Submitted to National Science Foundation,” July 1974; “Sine Summation Formula Synthesis,” ca. 1976; and “Progress Report on the Development of the FM-type Musical Instrument for the period of March 1979 to February 1980.”
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
John M. Chowning, professor emeritus of music at Stanford, developed the technique for creating digital sounds in the late 1960s which was patented and then licensed to Yamaha in 1973. He earned his bachelor of music at Wittenberg University in 1959, studied composition with Nadia Boulanger in Paris, and earned his Ph.D. at Stanford in 1966. He was the founding director in 1975 of Stanford's Center for Computer Research in Music and Acoustics.
Description of the Collection
Collection consists largely of correspondence between Chowning, the Yamaha Corporation, and the Technology Licensing Office at Stanford, 1974-97; other items include patents and related documents, 1978-87, technical writings (not all by Chowning), 1974-87, publications and leaflets on Yamaha products, and miscellaneous notes. The technical writings include “Excerpts from Computer Music Proposal Submitted to National Science Foundation,” July 1974; “Sine Summation Formula Synthesis,” ca. 1976; and “Progress Report on the Development of the FM-type Musical Instrument for the period of March 1979 to February 1980.”
Synthesizer (Musical instrument); Computer music.; Chowning, John M.; Risset, Jean-Claude; Stanford University. Office of Technology Licensing; Yamaha Corporation.; Stanford University. Center for Computer Research in Music and Acoustics; Chowning, John M.
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2008-177
  - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1995-1997 and undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Technical writings, 1974-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Technical writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Publications and leaflets (Yamaha products) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Patents and related documents, 1978-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Additional papers, Accession ARCH-2015-087
  - John Chowning & Jean-Claude Rissette: pionniers de la computer music, 2014 Sep 24-26; 2 computer file(s) (Box 1)
  - John Chowning & Jean-Claude Rissette: pionniers de la computer music (program), 2014 Sep 24-26 (Box 1)
- Additional papers, Accession ARCH-2016-053
  - Niels J. Reimers correspondence re patent application, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - FM Hardware, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stanford visit to IRCAM, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Theremin visit, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)